Ameya Patil

ameyapatil249@gmail.com | ameyabp.github.io | linkedin/ameyaspatil | +1(301) 674 1837

Research Interests

My research interests lie in building interactive data analysis systems for environmental science contexts like analyzing earth system models or animal tracking data. Accordingly, my work lies in the intersection of databases, data visualization and human-computer interaction. Additionally, I am also interested in visualization perception research, specifically regarding uncertainty visualization.

EDUCATION

University of Washington, Seattle (UW)

WA, USA

Ph.D. in Computer Science, Advised by **Dr. Leilani Battle**, GPA: 4.00/4.00

Sept 2021 - Present

- Relevant Coursework: Computing for Conservation

University of Maryland, College Park (UMD)

MD, USA

Ph.D. in Computer Science, Advised by **Dr. Leilani Battle**, GPA: 4.00/4.00

Jan 2021 - May 2021

- Relevant Coursework: Game Design

University of Maryland, College Park (UMD)

MD, USA

M.S. in Computer Science, GPA: 3.84/4.00

Aug 2018 - Dec 2020

Relevant Coursework: Machine Learning, Geometric Computer Vision, Advanced Computer Graphics,
 Physically Based Modelling, Simulation & Animation, Interactive Data Analytics, Computational Geometry,
 Interactive Technologies in HCI, Database System Architecture and Implementation

Birla Institute of Technology and Science - Pilani (BITS)

Goa, India

B.E. (Honors) in Computer Science, GPA: 8.24/10.00

Aug 2012 - May 2016

- Electives: Data Mining, Data Storage Technologies and Networks, Creative Multimedia

Publications

- 1. A. Patil, Z. Rand, T. Branch, L. Battle, "WhaleVis: A New Visualization Tool for the IWC Catch Database", International Whaling Commission SC/69A/GDR/04, 2023. archive.iwc.int/SC/69A/GDR/04
- 2. A. Patil, G. Richer, C. Jermaine, D. Moritz, J.-D. Fekete, "Studying Early Decision Making for Progressive Bar Charts", IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics, 2023. DOI: 10.1109/TVCG.2022.3209426
- 3. A. Aguinaldo, P.-Y. Chiang, A. Gain, A. Patil, K. Pearson and S. Feizi, "Compressing GANs using Knowledge Distillation", CoRR, vol. abs/1902.00159, 2019. arXiv:1902.00159

EXPERIENCE

National Center for Atmospheric Research

Boulder, USA

Data Visualization Intern, advised by **Dr. Helen Kershaw**, **Dr. Moha El Gharamti** and **Marlee Smith**

Summer 2023

- Designed HydroVis an interactive analysis dashboard for the WRF-Hydro hydrological forecasting model
- Implemented the dashboard backend using Python-Flask and XArray, and the renderer using D3.js
- Integrated the dashboard with the Data Assimilation Research Testbed (DART) tool at NCAR

AVIZ, Inria Saclay, France Summer 2021

Research Intern, advised by Dr. Jean-Daniel Fekete

Worked on understanding the efficacy of confidence intervals for decision making using progressive bar charts

- Proposed and studied the efficacy of two new visualization designs for progressive bar charts
- Studied the performance of humans vs automated statistical test for the task of answering questions based on progressive visualizations

Fraunhofer CESE MD, USA

Research Assistant Intern, advised by Dr. Marcel Schäfer

Summer 2019

- Worked as Java developer on the PocketSecurity project which collects data to perform user behaviour analysis
- Identified and implemented critical data probes to be collected for better analysis and improved existing probes

NVIDIA Pune, India

System Software Engineer - C/C++

July 2016 - July 2018

- Worked as developer for Shadowplay a gameplay sharing app to recrod, screenshot, broadcast and coplay video games
- Worked on multi-threaded and multi-processes features, GPU driver code and render pipeline
- Enhanced and monitored the automated software testing suite and guided an intern for the same

NVIDIA Pune, India July 2015 - Dec 2015 Intern

- Device Filter Drivers C/C++: Implemented end-to-end user input redirection from input devices to a specific application using filter drivers and device notifications
- Z-buffer Python: Implemented aesthetic visual effects such as zoom burst using the depth data of images

Projects

Visualizing the History of Commercial Whaling

Sept 2022 - Apr - 2023

Developed an interactive dashboard to visualize the whale hunting database maintained by the International Whaling Commission. The data is modelled as a network graph where the nodes represent the hunt locations and the edges represent the hunting search effort. This facilitates correctly estimating spatial distribution of whale populations.

• Physically Based Clustering Visualization

Oct 2019 - Dec 2019

Implemented a data analysis/visualization tool with interactions modelled on real-life physical forces using the D3-Force API. The specific use case targeted was evaluating word embeddings created by different methods, where words closer in the vector space belonged to the same cluster.

Adding shadows to a scene using CNN

April 2019 - May 2019

Trained a network to generate shadows in a scene, given the scene without shadows, the depth map and the light source position map. Used the pix2pix model for the task.

• GoRoutines vs OpenMP

Oct 2018 - Dec 2018

Comparatively evaluated the parallelization constructs of Go language and OpenMP using various task distribution schemes among threads. 2D image convolution operation was used for the study.

• Data Sonification Jan 2016 - Apr 2016

Investigated and implemented possible correlations between digital images and digital sounds for image encoding. Characterized aural encoding channels similar to visual encoding channels.

• LEAP Motion App Development

Mar 2015 - Apr 2015

Programmed the LEAP Motion sensor to create a hand gesture based virtual music instrument dashboard. Used JAVA Swing for the UI and MIDI files for the audio.

	-	~		~
1	'H'. Δ	CH	LNI	1

• Head Teaching Assistant at University of Maryland, College Park Computer Systems Architecture (CMSC411) Fall 2018, Fall 2019, Fall 2020

 Teaching Assistant at University of Maryland, College Park Introduction to Data Visualization (CMSC498O) Spring 2019, Spring 2020

• Teaching Assistant at University of Maryland, College Park Advanced Data Structures (CMSC420) Spring 2021

SKILLS

• Programming Languages: C, C++, Java, Python, Javascript

- Programming Languages: C, C++, Java, Python, Javascrip
- Libraries/Frameworks: D3.js, OpenCV, MPI, OpenMP
 Miscellaneous: DSLR Photography, Adobe Lightroom

Marathi: NativeHindi: FluentEnglish: Fluent

LANGUAGES

SCHOLARSHIPS AND AWARDS

• Birla Institute of Technology and Science - Pilani Merit Scholarship

2012

• Maharashtra State Board of Secondary and Higher Secondary Education Scholarship

2012

Extracurricular Activities

• University of Washington, Seattle K-12

2022

- Participated in the UW, Seattle K-12 outreach program by presenting my research work to high school students
- Volunteer at Ekta Nagar Residents Welfare Association

 Aided in the organisation of community activities and administrative affairs of my residential society

2017 - 2018

• Organising Committee Member at Quark (BITS - Pilani Goa Technical Festival)
Directed the photo and video coverage of the technical festival spanned over 3 days

2015

• Videography intern at Zone Startups India Created an advertisement video, and clicked portfolio photographs for Zone Startups India June 2015

• Member at The Department of Photography, BITS-Pilani Goa

2012 - 2015

Performed photo and video coverage of campus events over 3 years and mentored new inductees